<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
  <?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC1034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5322 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5322.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5731 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5731.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8126 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8126.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8174 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC8499 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8499.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-flanagan-regext-datadictionary-01" category="std">

<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>

  <front>
    <title>DNS Data Dictionary</title>

    <author initials="H." surname="Flanagan" fullname="Heather Flanagan" role="editor">
      <organization>Edgemoor Research Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>

          <code></code>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <facsimile></facsimile>
        <email>hlf@sphericalcowconsulting.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <author initials="S." surname="Crocker" fullname="Steve Crocker">
      <organization>Edgemoor Research Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street></street>
          <city></city>

          <code></code>
          <country></country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <facsimile></facsimile>
        <email>steve@shinkuro.com</email>

      </address>
    </author>

    <date year="2021" month="November" day="18"/>

    <area>Applications</area>
    <workgroup></workgroup>
    <keyword>Internet-Draft</keyword>

    <abstract>

<t>Multiple applications related to the domain name system are built around a
  list of data elements.  There is currently no unified public list of these
  data elements, nor is there an organized and independent change control
  process.  This document codifies the multiple similar but not quite
  identical lists of data elements into a neutral DNS Data Dictionary to be
  maintained as an independent IANA Registry.</t>

    </abstract>
   </front>

   <middle>


<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">

<t>The DNS Data Dictionary provides a common set of names and definitions for
  data elements which may be used in a DNS related protocol.  The dictionary
  is intended to be inclusive and not obligatory.  That is, the existence of
  a data element in this dictionary does not imply the data element must be used
  or recognized in any particular protocol. The items in this dictionary should
  represent the union for what is in existing relevant protocols, and should
  prevent divergence in new protocols. We also expect that each
  application or protocol may have additional requirements specific to the
  application or protocol. Such additional requirements should be
  documented as part of the application or protocol specification.</t>

<t>The data dictionary currently has thirty-one data elements.
  These data elements include the DNS records, the detailed status of a
  registration to the details for each of the contacts, and the account details
  and payment history.  The proposed IANA registry lists standard data elements
  and their syntax for inclusion in the files.</t>

<t>We expect the DNS data dictionary to evolve to meet the needs of various
  applications.  With the exception of correction of errors, we expect the
  changes to the DNS Data Dictionary to be additions as opposed to deletions or
  changes.</t>

<t>[Comment: We are looking for additional authors and contributors to add to
  and improve the data dictionary, keeping in line with the RFC Series Editor
  statement on authorship. <eref target="https://www.rfc-editor.org/pipermail/rfc-interest/2015-May/008869.html"/>]</t>

<section anchor="requirements-language" title="Requirements Language">

<t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD",
  "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
  document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/>
  <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as
  shown here.</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="data-element-specification" title="Data Element Specification">

<t>Each data element is a single unit of information that can be collected
and compared during the registration process. The primary purposes of
the IANA registry of data elements are to ensure that each data element
is assigned a unique name and that the syntax of each data element is
specified.</t>

<t>Each data element is assigned to an element type to organize the
taxonomy of the data dictionary.</t>

<t>The name of the data element MUST be unique and this characteristic MUST
be enforced by the registry. The character encoding recommendation for
data elements is specified in Section 3.</t>

<t>The subsections below comprise an initial list of known data elements
commonly being used in the templates. The title of the subsection is the
data element name for the data element. The combination of data element
type and data element name MUST be unique and MUST be processed as case
insensitive in the IANA registry.</t>

<section anchor="element-name-domain-name" title="Element name: Domain Name">

<t>This is the domain name in an EPP <xref target="RFC5731"/> domain object and
it MUST be in A-Label format.</t>

<t>See also "Domain name" in <xref target="RFC8499"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-registry" title="Element name: Registry">

<t>The name of the registry. This data element is text/string with no
naming convention enforced.</t>

<t>See also "Registry" in <xref target="RFC8499"/>.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="element-name-ns" title="Element name: NS">
  <t>The authoritative name server for the domain.<xref target="RFC1034"/></t>
  <t>See also "Authoritative server" in <xref target="RFC8499"/></t>
</section>

<section anchor="element-name-reg-creation-date" title="Element name: Registration Creation Date">
  <t>The EPP status code (&lt;domain:crDate&gt;) for the domain registration creation date.<xref target="RFC5731"/></t>
</section>

<section anchor="element-name-reg-expiration-date" title="Element name: Registration Expiration Date">
  <t>The EPP status code (&lt;domain:exDate&gt;) for the domain registration expiration date.<xref target="RFC5731"/></t>
</section>

<section anchor="element-name-reg-updated-date" title="Element name: Registration Updated Date">
  <t>The EPP status code (&lt;domain:upDate&gt;) for the domain registration updated date.<xref target="RFC5731"/></t>

</section>

<section anchor="element-name-reg-transfer-date" title="Element name: Registration Transfer Date">
  <t>The EPP status code (&lt;domain:trDate&gt;) for the domain registration transfer date.<xref target="RFC5731"/></t>
</section>

<section anchor="element-name-protection" title="Element name: Protection">
  <t>The level of protection assigned to a domain registration.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="element-name-nexus" title="Element name: Nexus">

<t>The country, community, or geographic location of the account holder.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-person" title="Element name: Person">

<t>Indication that the rules regarding this registration apply as per the
registrant being a legal person or a natural person.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-personal" title="Element name: Personal">

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-status-locks" title="Element name: Status &amp; Locks">

<t>The EPP Status codes (ex: clientTransferProhibited) related to domain.<xref target="RFC5731"/></t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-source-method" title="Element name: Source &amp; Method">

<t>The back pointer from registry to registrant.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-payment-history" title="Element name: Payment History">

<t>Information related to the customer’s financial exchanges.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-transaction-history" title="Element name: Transaction History">

<t>[Is this same as 2.4.2?]</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-user-account-id" title="Element name: User Account ID">

<t>This is a customer ID at the registrar, reseller, or privacy/proxy
provider, respectively.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-reserved" title="Element name: Reserved">

<t>[this field is an artifact of prior use which was determined to not be
necessary, but the field was left intact for future use]</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-name" title="Element name: Name">

<t>Individual name is represented using character strings. These strings
have a specified minimum length and a specified maximum length.
Individual names MAY be provided in either UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"/> or a subset
of UTF-8 that can be represented in 7-bit ASCII, depending on local
needs.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-org" title="Element name: Org">

<t>Organization name is represented using character strings. These strings
have a specified minimum length and a specified maximum length.
Organizational names MAY be provided in either UTF-8 <xref target="RFC3629"/> or a subset of UTF-8 that can be represented in 7-bit ASCII, depending on local needs.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-street" title="Element name: Street">

<t>Postal street address, formatted as per <xref target="ISO19160-4"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-city" title="Element name: City">

<t>Postal city address, formatted as per <xref target="ISO19160-4"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-stateprovince" title="Element name: State/Province">

<t>Postal state or province address, formatted as per <xref target="ISO19160-4"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-postal-code" title="Element name: Postal code">

<t>Postal code, formatted as per <xref target="ISO19160-4"/>. Contact postal codes are
represented using character strings. These strings have a specified
minimum length and a specified maximum length.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-country" title="Element name: Country">

<t>Country code identifier. Contact country identifiers are represented
using two-character identifiers specified in <xref target="ISO3166-1"/>.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-phone" title="Element name: Phone">

<t>Telephone number structure is derived from structures defined in
<xref target="ITU.E164.2005"/>. Telephone numbers described in this mapping are
character strings that MUST begin with a plus sign (“+”, ASCII value
0x002B), followed by a country code defined in [ITU.E164.2005],
followed by a dot (“.”, ASCII value 0x002E), followed by a sequence of
digits representing the telephone number. An optional “x” attribute is
provided to note telephone extension information.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-phone-ext" title="Element name: Phone ext">

<t>This field is intended to represent an “extension” within the phone
number to reach the specific person or role desk telephone, appropriate
queue or mailbox after successfully dialing the Phone element.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-fax" title="Element name: Fax">

<t>Fax telephone number structure is derived from structures defined in
[ITU.E164.2005]. Telephone numbers described in this mapping are
character strings that MUST begin with a plus sign (“+”, ASCII value
0x002B), followed by a country code defined in <xref target="ITU.E164.2005"/>,
followed by a dot (“.”, ASCII value 0x002E), followed by a sequence of
digits representing the telephone number.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-fax-ext" title="Element name: Fax ext">

<t>This field is an “extension” within a phone tree or PBX that is
necessary to connect to a fax machine after successfully dialing the fax
element.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="element-name-email" title="Element name: Email">
  <t>Email address syntax is defined in <xref target="RFC5322"/>.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="element-name-emailorphone" title="Element name: Email_or_phone">
  <t>There is a requirement that either the phone or email element have been
    confirmed reachable, which this field is intended to represent.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="element-name-uniqueid" title="Element name: Registry UniqueID">
  <t>This field represents server-unique identifiers assigned to entities, such
    as clients and contacts. These identifiers are character strings that
    typically have a specified minimum length, a specified maximum length, and a
    specified format.</t>
</section>

</section>
<section anchor="iana-considerations" title="IANA Considerations">

<t>This section describes the format of the IANA Registration Report</t>

<t>Registry, which has two tables described below, and the procedures</t>

<t>used to populate and manage the registry entries.</t>

<section anchor="report-specification" title="Report Specification">

<t>This registry uses the “Specification Required” policy described in
   <xref target="RFC8126"/>. An English language version of the extension
   specification is required in the registry, though non-English versions of the
   specification may also be provided.</t>

<t>The “Specification Required” policy implies review by a “designated expert”.
  Section 5.2 of RFC 8126 describes the role of designated experts and the
  function they perform.</t>

<section anchor="designated-expert-evaluation-criteria" title="Designated Expert
  Evaluation Criteria">

<t>A high-level description of the role of the designated expert is described in
  Section 5.2 of RFC 8126. Specific guidelines for the appointment of designated
  experts and the evaluation of a new data element is provided here.</t>

<t>The IESG SHOULD appoint a small pool of individuals (perhaps 3 - 5) to serve
  as designated experts, as described in Section 5.2 of RFC 8126. The pool
  should have a single administrative chair who is appointed by the IESG. The
  designated experts should use the existing regext mailing list
  (regext@ietf.org) for public discussion of registration requests. This implies
  that the mailing list should remain open after the work of the REGEXT working
  group has concluded.</t>

<t>The results of the evaluation should be shared via email with the registrant
  and the regext mailing list. Issues discovered during the evaluation can be
  corrected by the registrant, and those corrections can be submitted to the
  designated experts until the designated experts explicitly decide to accept or
  reject the registration request. The designated experts must make an explicit
  decision and that decision must be shared via email with the registrant and
  the regext mailing list. If the specification for a data element or report is
  an IETF Standards Track document, no review is required by the designated
  expert.</t>

<t>Designated experts should be permissive in their evaluation of requests for
  data elements and reports that have been implemented and deployed by at least
  one registry. This implies that it may indeed be possible to register multiple
  data elements or reports that provide the same functionality. Requests to
  register data elements or reports that have not been deployed should be
  evaluated with a goal of reducing duplication. A potential registrant who
  submits a request to register a new data element or report that includes
  similar functionality to existing data elements or reports should be made
  aware of the existing data elements and reports. The registrant should be
  asked to reconsider their request given the existence of similar data elements
  or reports. Should they decline to do so, perceived similarity should not be a
  sufficient reason for rejection as long as all other requirements are met.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="registration-procedure" title="Registration Procedure">

<t>The registry contains information describing each registered data element or
  report. Registry entries are created and managed by sending forms to IANA that
  describe the data element or report for the registry entry.</t>

<section anchor="required-information" title="Required Information">

<t>The required information must be formatted consistently using the following
  registration form. Form field names and values may appear on the same line.</t>

<section anchor="data-element-definition" title="Data Element Definition">

<t>Name of data element type</t>

<t>
    MUST be unique within the registry, enforced to be unique, and MUST be
    processed as case insensitive
</t>

<t>Name of data element</t>

<t>
    MUST be unique within the registry, enforced to be unique, and MUST be
    processed as case insensitive
</t>

<t>Reference document</t>

<t>
    MUST define the data element, SHOULD be a URL to a RFC, and SHOULD include
    the section number (or other detailed internal document reference), MAY be a
    URL to any document available under equivalent terms
</t>

<t>Registrant</t>

<t>
    Will be IESG for initial entries and all Standards Track specifications;
    otherwise as specified by the registran
</t>

<t>Status</t>

<t>
    MUST be one of active, inactive, or unknown
</t>

</section>
</section>
<section anchor="registration-processing" title="Registration Processing">

<t>Registrants should send each registration form to IANA with a single record
  for incorporation into the registry. Send the form via email to iana@iana.org
  or complete the online form found on the IANA web site. The subject line
  should indicate whether the enclosed form represents an insertion of a new
  record (indicated by the word “INSERT” in the subject line) or a replacement
  of an existing record (indicated by the word “MODIFY” in the subject line). At
  no time can a record be deleted from the registry. On receipt of the
  registration request, IANA will initiate review by the designated expert(s) if
  appropriate, who will evaluate the request using the criteria in Section 3.1.1
  in consultation with the regext mailing list.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="updating-report-definition-registry-entries" title="Updating
  Report Definition Registry Entries">

<t>When submitting changes to existing registry entries, include text in the
  “Notes” field of the registration form describing the change. Under normal
  circumstances, registry entries are only to be updated by the registrant. If
  the registrant becomes unavailable or otherwise unresponsive, the designated
  expert can submit a registration form to IANA to update the registrant
  information. Entries can change state from “Active” to “Inactive” and back
  again as long as state-change requests conform to the processing requirements
  identified in this document. In addition to entries that become “Inactive” due
  to a lack of implementation, entries for which a specification becomes
  consistently unavailable over time should be marked “Inactive” by the
  designated expert until the specification again becomes reliably available.</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="initial-assignments" title="Initial assignments">

<section anchor="data-element-definition-in-iana-registry" title="Data Element
  Definition in IANA Registry">

<t>—- BEGIN FORM —-</t>

<t>Name of data element:</t>

<t>Domain Name</t>

<t>Reference:</t>

<t>This RFC Section 2.1.</t>

<t>Registrant:</t>

<t>IESG, iesg@ietf.org</t>

<t>Status:</t>

<t>Active</t>

<t>—- END FORM —-</t>

<t>—- BEGIN FORM —-</t>

<t>Name of data element:</t>

<t>…………</t>

<t>Reference:</t>

<t>This RFC Section $2.n</t>

<t>Registrant:</t>

<t>IESG, iesg@ietf.org</t>

<t>Status:</t>

<t>Active</t>

<t>—- END FORM —-</t>

</section>
</section>
</section>
<section anchor="security-considerations" title="Security Considerations">

<t>This specification does not consider the issues of distribution or access to
  the reports that are created and thus does not introduce any new security
  oncerns that are not already present in the local environment in which the
  report is created.</t>

<t>A security principle to keep in mind as new reports are developed is that it
  is considered a bad practice to report or disclose security information. In
  the case of the registration system upon which this reporting mechanism is
  based, the authInfo code is a specific example of a data element that SHOULD
  NOT be included in a report.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="privacy-considerations" title="Privacy Considerations">

<t>This specification defines a mechanism for policy comparison based on data in
  a registration system. Some of that data is likely to be considered personally
  identifiable information (PII) and thus would be subject to privacy protection
  according to an applicable privacy regulation. It is outside the scope of this
  specification to address those specific concerns. Implementors are urged to
  consider these issues with their local legal authority and develop appropriate
  requirements for their work.</t>

</section>
<section anchor="internationalization-considerations" title="Internationalization Considerations">

<t>The character encoding for the file contents MUST use UTF-8. Throughout this
  document A-LABEL is indicated as a SHOULD and that MUST be interpreted as
  follows. All domain name labels MUST be in A-LABEL format if it is possible to
  represent it as an A-LABEL, otherwise U-LABEL MAY be used.</t>

</section>

<section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>With many thanks to James Galvin and Rod Rasmussen for their advice and
  feedback on this data dictionary.</t>

</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">

&RFC1034;
&RFC2119;
&RFC3629;
&RFC5322;
&RFC5731;
&RFC8126;
&RFC8174;
&RFC8499;

<reference anchor="ISO3166-1" >
  <front>
    <title>ISO3166-1: Codes for the representation of names of countries and
      their subdivisions -- Part1: Country codes</title>
    <author>
      <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2006"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ISO19160-4" >
  <front>
    <title>ISO19160-4: Addressing — Part 4: International postal address
      components and template language</title>
    <author>
      <organization>International Organization for Standardization</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="November" year="2017"/>
  </front>
</reference>

<reference anchor="ITU.E164.2005" >
  <front>
    <title>ITU-T Recommendation E.164: The international public telecommunication numbering plan</title>
    <author>
      <organization>International Telecommunication Union</organization>
    </author>
    <date month="February" year="2005"/>
  </front>
</reference>



</references>


</back>
</rfc>
